<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Catch22</title>
    <link>http://catch22.tech/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Catch22</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 08:54:29 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://catch22.tech/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Is React Native Right for your Business?</title>
      <link>http://catch22.tech/post/is-react-native-right-for-your-business/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 08:54:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://catch22.tech/post/is-react-native-right-for-your-business/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction:b51614b30bcf098d8cf3008a650f5d66&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you decide that your business needs a mobile app in spite of &lt;a href=&#34;http://catch22.tech/post/your-business-probably-shouldnt-build-a-mobile-app/&#34;&gt;the warning I&amp;rsquo;ve given&lt;/a&gt;, you should consider using &lt;a href=&#34;https://facebook.github.io/react-native/&#34;&gt;React Native&lt;/a&gt; for your project. React Native is a new tool for cross-platform mobile development. The tool allows developers to share code between Android and iOS devices, thereby reducing development time. While React Native can reduce development costs, using the tool is riskier than native mobile development and some features that are available in the newest versions of iOS and Android may not be available through React Native. This report discusses these tradeoffs in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lower-development-costs:b51614b30bcf098d8cf3008a650f5d66&#34;&gt;Lower-development Costs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because React Native allows developers to share much of the code between the two platforms, there can be significant development cost savings. &lt;a href=&#34;https://code.facebook.com/posts/1189117404435352/react-native-for-android-how-we-built-the-first-cross-platform-react-native-app/&#34;&gt;Facebook has reported&lt;/a&gt; that they’ve been able to share up to 85% of their code across Android and iOS in one of their smaller applications. Some have even suggested that the code reuse between the two platforms could be even higher than this.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;risk:b51614b30bcf098d8cf3008a650f5d66&#34;&gt;Risk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;worrisome:b51614b30bcf098d8cf3008a650f5d66&#34;&gt;Worrisome&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;React Native is not maintained by Apple or Google. Because of this, there&amp;rsquo;s a risk that support for the tool may eventually be dropped. As the following Google Trends graph suggests, Phonegap, a similar cross-platform application development tool that is not supported by Google and Apple may be on its way to this fate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://catch22.tech/images/phonegap-trend.png&#34; alt=&#34;downward trend&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;React Native is also a risky proposition because it uses Javascript, a language and ecosystem that is known for being a particularly volatile.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;promising:b51614b30bcf098d8cf3008a650f5d66&#34;&gt;Promising&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;React Native is partially a response to the failures of Phonegap as a mobile application development tool.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; As the name implies, React Native actually allows developers to use native views in their applications. Phonegap, on the other hand, only allowed developers to use webviews, views that don’t look and feel like the views we’ve come to know and love in all of our favorite applications. It’s promising that React Native has recognized the shortcomings of Phonegap as a tool. Hopefully, this recognition will save React Native from becoming irrelevant, a fate that Phonegap may not be able to escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;React Native is maintained by Facebook. They&amp;rsquo;ve invested heavily in the project, and they appear to be happy with the results. As I’ve said before, they’ve reported that they’ve been able to share up to 85% of their code across Android and iOS. They are using React Native in some of Facebook’s apps, including the main Facebook app.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; This suggests that they will continue investing in and maintaining the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;features:b51614b30bcf098d8cf3008a650f5d66&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because React Native is a 3rd-party tool that’s not developed by Google and Apple, there may be some delay between when a feature is released for the new versions of iOS and Android and when that feature becomes available in React Native. If it’s critical that your application be on the cutting edge of new features that are available on mobile devices, React Native may not be a good fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;want-to-know-more:b51614b30bcf098d8cf3008a650f5d66&#34;&gt;Want to know more?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;d like to talk more about whether React Native is a good fit for your development project, check us out at Catch22, an application development company. Checkout our landing page and &lt;a href=&#34;http://catch22.tech/#download&#34;&gt;leave us your email &lt;/a&gt; so we can setup a meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes:b51614b30bcf098d8cf3008a650f5d66&#34;&gt;Notes:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adam Miskiewicz at Chalk and Chisle, a development agency that’s done work with the Discovery Channel and Nike is an example of someone who thinks that 85% is not even the upper-bound on the potential for code reused.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@ericclemmons/javascript-fatigue-48d4011b6fc4#.z5q5db7m1&#34;&gt;There’s a Medium article&lt;/a&gt; that pretty well captures this sentiment. Interestingly, the article also suggests that 2016 will be the year that the javascript ecosystem starts to stabilize.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://code.facebook.com/posts/1014532261909640/react-native-bringing-modern-web-techniques-to-mobile/&#34;&gt;In the blog post announcing React Native&lt;/a&gt;, Facebook says this about Phonegap-like development tools: &amp;ldquo;What we really want is the user experience of the native mobile platforms&amp;hellip;There are a few ways we can probably achieve this&amp;hellip;One possibility is to use WebViews inside simple native wrapper applications. We tried this a few years back&amp;hellip;Unfortunately, because all the rendering is done using web tech, we can&amp;rsquo;t produce a truly native user experience.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://facebook.github.io/react-native/showcase.html&#34;&gt;the react native showcase&lt;/a&gt; for a list of apps that use react native.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Your Business Probably Shouldn&#39;t Build a Mobile App</title>
      <link>http://catch22.tech/post/your-business-probably-shouldnt-build-a-mobile-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 17:49:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://catch22.tech/post/your-business-probably-shouldnt-build-a-mobile-app/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sexy-but-not-cheap:4d517dacb2f84b7e5ca7da4f8d11cb24&#34;&gt;Sexy, but not cheap&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mobile apps are sexy. Whenever I tell people that I develop mobile applications, their eyes light up. They ask me what apps I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on and they often pitch me on a &amp;ldquo;million dollar idea&amp;rdquo; for an app. Planet of the Apps, a new reality TV show about mobile application development, is further evidence that people are fascinated with mobile applications and the businesses that are built around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its easy to get caught up in the app hype. Huge companies like Facebook, Uber, and Airbnb may make us think that building a mobile app can result in huge benefits for our businesses. While this is true in some cases, the reality is that building a mobile application for your business can be a big waste of time and money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can start to see how expensive mobile applications are if we look at the average salary of a mobile application developer. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.glassdoor.com/Salaries/mobile-developer-salary-SRCH_KO0,16.htm&#34;&gt;According to Glassdoor&lt;/a&gt;, the national average yearly salary of a mobile developer is $76,061, which leads to an hourly rate of about $36.50. With just one week of full-time work, your mobile app already has a price tag of $1460. If you want to build your application for both Android and iOS, you &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; need to double that price tag because the code that works for Android won&amp;rsquo;t work for iOS.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, these salary surveys are just that: surveys of people who are working at companies with a salary. If you hire a freelance developer, however, you may find that the hourly rate they charge is much higher than the rate you see for salaried employees. The reason for this is that freelance developers need to cover the cost of their own insurance and other benefits (like vacation time) that are already included in the compensation package of salaried employees. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard experienced freelance developers advise new freelancers to charge twice the hourly rate they would have if they were regular salaried employees, and I&amp;rsquo;ve known developers who have charged $200/hr for their services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even large companies like Google and Facebook are sensitive to the development costs of mobile applications. Both companies have created tools that allow them to share code between iOS and Android phones.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; If these large companies are worried about development costs, you and your small business should be worried too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-golden-age-is-over:4d517dacb2f84b7e5ca7da4f8d11cb24&#34;&gt;The Golden Age is Over&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kpcb.com/&#34;&gt;KPCB&lt;/a&gt;, an venture capital firm that invests in internet startups, has published a report that points out that the growth of mobile device shipments is rapidly decelerating and that the money spent in Apple and Google&amp;rsquo;s app stores has been shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://catch22.tech/images/decelerating-growth.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;decelerating mobile device shipment&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://catch22.tech/images/shrinking-revenue.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;shrinking revenue&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://qz.com/253618/most-smartphone-users-download-zero-apps-per-month/&#34;&gt;Quartz also reports&lt;/a&gt; that most mobile phone users are downloading 0 apps per month. Presumably, this fact was the central motivation for Google to release &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.android.com/topic/instant-apps/index.html&#34;&gt;its new &amp;ldquo;Instant App&amp;rdquo; feature for Android&lt;/a&gt; this past summer, a feature that allows users to run an Android application without downloading it.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; It may be sexy to talk and think about mobile apps, but for many mobile phone users, apps aren&amp;rsquo;t sexy enough to even download let alone pay for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-you-really-need-an-app:4d517dacb2f84b7e5ca7da4f8d11cb24&#34;&gt;Do you really need an app?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, mobile apps are expensive and people today are less willing to download and spend money on them. Does that mean your business can&amp;rsquo;t benefit from a mobile application? Not necessarily. The point here is just that it&amp;rsquo;s worth considering whether there&amp;rsquo;s a better way to solve your business&amp;rsquo; problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many cases, developing a responsive web application may be a better choice for your business. Responsive web apps don&amp;rsquo;t require separate code for Android and iOS and with the advent of web application frameworks like angular and react, it can be cheaper and faster to develop a web application instead of a native mobile app. Moreover, web applications offer many of the same benefits native mobile apps have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Google I/O conference app is a nice case-in-point here. The following video is of the responsive web app for Google I/O, a yearly developer conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;video src=&#34;http://catch22.tech/video/google-io-webapp.mp4&#34; controls/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see the web app is pretty slick. To be sure, the experience is not as nice as a native mobile app, but money doesn&amp;rsquo;t grow on trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, a web app can, in some cases, deliver many of the same benefits as a native mobile app without the big price tag. Because of this, I recommend that you only build a mobile application if your app needs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mobile-specific UI gestures like &amp;ldquo;swipe&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;pinch to zoom&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;complicated offline data storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;access to the mobile device&amp;rsquo;s sensors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There might be some other cases where it does make sense to build a mobile app instead of a web app, but I think this list covers the most common cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re pretty tech-savy, you may have some objections to this recommendation. You might ask, &amp;ldquo;But what about push notifications?&amp;rdquo; Turns out web apps can do that.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; Then you might ask, &amp;ldquo;What about offline access?&amp;rdquo; Web apps can do that. In fact, the video that you saw above on the left demonstrates a web application that allows offline access. Finally, you might ask, &amp;ldquo;But what if I need the user&amp;rsquo;s location data?&amp;rdquo; Web apps can do that too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:4d517dacb2f84b7e5ca7da4f8d11cb24&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re considering building an app for your business, don&amp;rsquo;t get caught up in the app hype. Consider whether a responsive web application may better suite your needs. Even if you decide a mobile app is right for you, if price is an issue for your business, consider hiring us at Catch22. Check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://catch22.tech&#34;&gt;our landing page for more info&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know a small business owner that&amp;rsquo;s looking to build a mobile app and you think this article will help them, please share it and save them some money!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;notes:4d517dacb2f84b7e5ca7da4f8d11cb24&#34;&gt;Notes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may not need to double this price tag if you&amp;rsquo;re using a cross-platform application development tool like &lt;a href=&#34;https://facebook.github.io/react-native/&#34;&gt;React Native&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;These tools are called &lt;a href=&#34;http://j2objc.org/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;java2Objc&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://facebook.github.io/react-native/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;React Native,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I suspect that Apple will copy this feature by next summer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t believe me? Visit facebook.com through your mobile browser and you&amp;rsquo;ll be prompted to allow push notifications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>